[SPEAKER_01]: I thought we can discuss the gradual training that is found in suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sometimes divided in different ways, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this is the usual.
[SPEAKER_01]: In Majjhima Nikaya, 107, it begins with
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it possible to describe a gradual training, a gradual practice and gradual progress in the dhamma and discipline?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha says, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he obtains a person to be tamed, he first disciplines him thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, come Bhikkhu, be virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: In some other suttas, it's also before that, you know, five precepts, eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it is, overall, that's the first step.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think the seeing fear in the slightest fault, being able to recognize a fault and then... Yeah, well, it's when it says restrained by the rules of patimokkha, like the rules that pertain to practice, not kind of the rules they were pertaining to like a social circumstances at the time, they all can be boiled down into eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or ten, if you want to forsake the handling of money and gold and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means it's not just for the monks, it's for anybody who wants to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it was presumed that by wearing robes you want to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what the Buddha would be addressing the monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even if you don't wear the robes today, you want to practice, rules of patimokkha apply to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not technically,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as in the spirit of eight precepts, yes, that's why whenever the Buddha would speak in the context outside of the like a monk saṅgha, speak about the virtue, he would talk about, you know, the like the eight precepts, the wise men of the old used to, you know, used to live by eight precepts all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they had such a long lifespan and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eight precepts is the bare minimum for beginning of that self-taming, self-sense-restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: The discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: The discipline, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, if you're a disciple, then there's the discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yes, yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are a lay follower, which means the one who trails behind out of devotion, that's where the five precepts are.
[SPEAKER_00]: They keep you from behaving like an animal, and you're making merit, and hopefully it will contribute towards your better birth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're the one who sees himself as as the one who practices the dhamma, the eight precepts are not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the the bare minimum, the basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the very first thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can substitute there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come here, Bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: You say, you want to practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, come here.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the discipline you have to take on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you take on that discipline, you need to start seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, that can be taken neurotically and probably would... will be initially, like... but that's... that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... you... you... you get used to the neurotic aspect of it, so you stop being bothered by neurosis, but you still remain seeing the... the value of that discipline and the fear of breaking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, if you're neurotic about breaking the precepts, that neurosis, that fear, will actually protect your discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like heriotica, fear and shame of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're afraid because of all the, you know, well, it will undo your very striving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that you want to develop through your practice can only be developed on the basis of discipline, and here you are willingly eroding that discipline through your choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: To break the rules.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start contemplating on the dangers of doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, naturally, you feel afraid of doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you won't be careless about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not afraid, that's when people become careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you stop paying close attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no fear motivating you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I kind of just jumped to the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting rid of the jhāna part.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll go to the jhāna part first.
[SPEAKER_01]: I work my way the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sure you can find an article or a teacher that will say, yes, you can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can bypass everything the Buddha said and go straight to jhāna part.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the jhāna, the results of that jhāna...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the common kind of misconception of even people that keep the precepts,
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't necessarily see the direct value of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't see how is this helping me tame myself, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, to what extent am I developing through keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They do it on account of, you know, faith, culture, tradition, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: meditation group they're part of, they might do it on account of external circumstances, motivating them to be restrained and keep the precepts because it's a good thing and so on, universally speaking, but deep down, they still hold the view that all these random things that they do will then, somehow, magically, contribute to the special experience of a jhāna or enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when that happens, the work's done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they don't see, basically, in other words, a direct work that they can do, through their own choices and developing the right context, that will inevitably have to result in jhāna and enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just do random work, that then they hope will produce the experience of jhāna or enlightenment, and then they won't have to do any work, because they're enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, let's go into the second step.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, once that person has perfected virtue,
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha disciplines him further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kambeku, guard the doors of your sense faculties.
[SPEAKER_01]: On seeing a form with the eye, do not grasp at its signs and features.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since if you were to leave the eye faculty, and so on, unguarded, evil, unwholesome states of covetousness and grief might invade you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Practice the way of its restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's already the, you know, what we call, colloquially, in our talks, like the peripheral awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't grasp the signs and features of that which you've seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like you don't see anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the signs and features of that which you... of a sense object you experience through your senses, they're always peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see signs and features.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like when you look at the signs that says, stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the letters, you see the color, you see the shape, but the significance of do not pass this line, you, specifically, don't come here, stop there, that's not in the sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you see that when your eyes see the sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the features of that sign, the significance of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, the meaning, the significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: The meaning, sure, the meaning, the significance, the signs, the features, the nimittas, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason I'm saying that is because often that practice of sense restraint is kind of conflated with this view of beating the sense down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, not looking, not looking, not touching, not breathing, nothing, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just compress it all, not see anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still you're not seeing the significance of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The signs and features of what you're doing, you're not seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you need to start basically recognizing the sense restraint to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are your restraining senses sure beforehand, as we said before, before you do actions, you decide, you already know whether it's going to be rooted in aversion, greed, and so on, and that if you know then it's rooted in greed, you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, say, sometimes things surprise you, pop up,
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressure arises that can become an ill will or sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you have a choice of that which you have seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have a choice whether you're choosing to dwell mentally on the signs and features that are suitable for increasing of passion in regard to it, or the signs and features of the...
[SPEAKER_00]: They are also...
[SPEAKER_00]: Both are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just what you choose to attend.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the signs and features that are not suitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, pressure has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't undo that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've seen things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, okay, like, I'm not in control of these eyes, only relatively speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can sort of foresee as much as I can and prevent, you know, things that are suitable for lust or aversion to arise for me to see and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, inevitably, things will happen because the organs are still there, untamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when that does happen, that's when we say you need to be able to allow things to endure without breaking your discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you have the discipline first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without, like, flirting with breaking of the rules, because you see the danger of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, without losing the context of the signs and features of that which pressures you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's on that level of signs and features, of things that pressure you, that mind either delights in sensuality, or tries to reject and get rid of the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the root of the whole problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were to be restraining your senses correctly, it's... it's kind of... well, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to be beating your eye down, you know, cutting your ears off and so on, so you'd never experience the object that might cause pressure of lust or disagreeability to arise in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is make sure, when your eye does see, is do here,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't dwell, delight, accept, welcome, entertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: The signs and features of what you've seen, they're basically making lust to increase.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sign of the beauty, the sign of agreeability, the sign of non-danger, the sign of friendly, homely, non-threatening.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things, all these significances are the sign of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if people were to truly see the danger of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that would ever be seen ever again as friendly, suitable, acceptable, pleasurable for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be seen like an ember, like a pit of burning embers.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can also see it with both those significances, what, you know, what you used to see it as.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: The significances are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like I must remove these significances of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must stop entertaining them
[SPEAKER_00]: And look for the other significances that are equally there, that I've been ignoring out of my habits of welcoming lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can look at the beautiful parts, which increases lust, or I can look at the ugly parts, which will calm things down.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not for the sake of getting rid of the beautiful parts, or for the sake of getting rid of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your eye is pressured, and your eye wants the parts that are beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is just keep projecting,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: In beautiful, if you develop your mind, you'll be able to see the ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not change the beautiful into ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same beautiful significances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see them as ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through them, you see the ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the threatening.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they do not grasp at its significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't take it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't entertain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't take it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The significance is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't take it up if you start attending the significances that you don't want to take up.
[SPEAKER_01]: The significance of danger, dissatisfaction...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you should grasp at those.
[SPEAKER_01]: The significance of danger, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, in a way, you don't grasp at its signs and features.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the thing that caused you lustful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, since if you were to leave the high faculty unguarded... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...evil, unwholesome states of covetousness might invade you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you... so, you're saying... the other signs and features...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, you don't start neutrally.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't begin your practice where you have this equal choice of beautiful and ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You begin by being fully gripped, pressured, taken up, welcome, entertained, of the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your sensory strain begins by not doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't grasp those features and then the other features will become more apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, that's... you then, by all means, grasp the feature of ugly, stick to it, and it will, like, develop dispassion into the arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncertainty, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those features are not visible because of the automatic grasp of lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatic grasp of getting rid of the discomfort, when you're touched by painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatic grasp of distraction when you're touched by neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, grasping at its signs and features means, in the beginning, means unguarded, you know, you're completely unguarded.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there is no more guarding there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're straight into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you guard your senses by maintaining the context that will basically make you abstain from just habitually grasping onto the beautiful aspects of what's given to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that pertains to any given sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in that sense, you won't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you will never be able to welcome and delight, with lust, the significance of danger in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you cannot have lust towards being free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you will develop those signs and features by not grasping that which is suitable for grasping.
[SPEAKER_00]: sensuality, signs of beautiful, welcoming it, entertaining it, giving in and trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like the underlying tendency.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't underlie everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot underlie everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: If underlying tendency to a lust can underlie everything, you won't be able to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you only need to abandon things that are underlined by... underlied by lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't grasp to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: The signs and features that are then revealed through not grasping, you can't grasp.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you can't delight in lust after jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly how you enter jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: By fully withdrawing yourself from signs and features that are grasped with lust, for lust, for increasing of that lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are only signs and features that can be grasped.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's where the grasping is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lustful aversion and delusion, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't grasp that, and then, by all means, try and grasp the signs of ugliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's just been mental cultivation of ugliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't grasp it with lust, but you can do it with effort, and, and, and discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, this is worth of keeping in my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: These signs and features, these nimittas, are worth to be developed and adhere to, because they result in dispassion everywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the third step, so to speak, the bhikkhu guards the doors of his sense faculties, then the tathāgata disciplines him further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kam bhikkhu, be moderate in eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reflecting wisely, you should take food neither for amusements nor for intoxication, nor for the sake of physical beauty and attractiveness, but only for endurance and continuance of this body, for ending discomfort and for assisting the holy life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Considering thus, I shall terminate old feelings without arousing new feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: I shall be healthy and blameless and shall live in comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: We covered the food thing in many other talks, but yeah, you just need to keep the... purify and sustain the right motivation, the reasons for you... you have to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you need to be moderate and reflect on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not... don't think that being moderate as in I'll eat half of this constitutes being moderate in eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll eat half of what I want to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically asceticism and more often than not it's misguided.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're moderating eating by not losing the context of the right reasons for your eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the Sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you moderating eating?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by eat every third morsel that you've taken.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're moderating eating by not eating for the reasons of beautification, by not eating for the reasons of enjoyment, by not eating for the reasons of distraction and sensual attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by eating for the reasons of sustaining the body, getting rid of discomfort, so that I can practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that motivation is something you can choose to keep in your mind or ignore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you keep that motivation in the mind, you won't have to worry about overeating or undereating, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You eat for the sake of getting rid of discomfort and you eat, you know, for the sake of being alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often moderation in eating gets conflated with, you know, I eat 20% and I reach...
[SPEAKER_00]: I fulfill that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you haven't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still equally ignorant of your motivation behind eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still... do you see that you are not eating?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the enjoyment... eating for the sake of enjoyment is still there, but you're just reducing it to 20%.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter if it's 100% or 20%, the centrality is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you really clear about the context behind your eating, on account of which you're eating, and where that context is rooted in?
[SPEAKER_00]: What are your intentions for taking this food?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it just because you really crave the taste?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's... it's... it's... like... nutritious for you?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that for a fact?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see why you are eating when you're eating?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you feel hunger when you're eating?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you worry about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I have to have no...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to have that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but if somebody takes that, I will not have it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that already it's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not eating for the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is any form of passion in regard to food, you're not eating for the right reasons, which means you need to be dwelling, contemplating and discerning those reasons more clearly, further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, okay, I will not eat ever again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is like, you know, I can't untie this knot, so I'll just cut it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's usually people's take on this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, just don't eat it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't eat it if you don't need to eat it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you think you'll be fine without eating it, fine, don't eat it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: But don't eat it because I can't figure out where my motivation is rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's throwing away the baby with the bathwater.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Re-rooting your motivation correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Re-rooting?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's, again, you begin by eating out of sensuality, beautification, craving to get rid of the discomfort, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not eating with a clear mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm eating because there is hunger.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I finish, I stop eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: And particularly, like, from that point of view, eating is quite a chore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what you eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having to eat, having to feel heavy afterwards for a bit, you know, having that food, that's all quite a nuisance, all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: A necessity, a chore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as you do that, you're gonna have those moments, you want to eat more, you want to... Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even if you have those moments, if you sustain the context,
[SPEAKER_00]: of eating for the right reasons, all those moments will disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like that simile given for samādhi, but it's the same principle, like heating up a pan, you're going to have moments of, you know, wet drops of this or this falling onto it, but if the pan is hot, sufficiently hot enough, none of that will linger on the pan.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will evaporate instantly or pretty quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't worry to try to, like, micromanage.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll take every second dish and not from a person on the left side of the road.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically like giants, complete, kind of skewed, getting all completely wound up because they didn't know how to approve the lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what they were doing, they were trying to control the circumstances and just rattle themselves through, like, constantly changing the requirements of the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that means you're looking at a completely wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll still be eating with lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're shunning the bait, you're doing it with lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lustfully, you don't want to engage with lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't sustain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sooner or later you have to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you don't eat, if you die, you died without revealing the true motivation behind the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you threw away the baby.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, after that, the Buddha disciplines the Bhikkhu further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come, Bhikkhu, be devoted to wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: During the day, while walking back and forth and sitting, purify your mind of obstructive states.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it goes into the, you know, first watch of the night, the second watch of the night, so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, we did that in the last few talks, didn't we?
[SPEAKER_00]: The overcoming hindrances and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like all... like the liability to lust, that liability to... to... to... aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can see that that passage is very commonly, very often found in suttas, how you purify your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how many contemporary practices you find teaching you how to purify your mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: They just tell you, focus on your nostrils, do this, be aware of what you're touching, what you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how is that purifying your mind of obstructive states?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just do this and I hope nothing arises in my mind that would be obstructive.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not purifying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just trying to prevent it, trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the purification, you can't just start with purifying your mind, because you won't even see your mind to begin with, let alone the states that are obstructive for the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to be well restrained with discipline, with the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to be celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see the danger in these faults.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you need to be guarding the sense faculties, not grasping, not welcoming, entertaining the signs and features that will be increasing lust, increasing aversion, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you need to be moderate in eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another practice that you do on top of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't just start being moderate in eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, as I described, it's moderate in eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about a quantity of bread you ate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about clarity of the motivation behind your eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for most people, that's completely invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because most people don't even keep their precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people are not celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people live with mind wet with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people don't guard their sense faculties correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't even see the signs and features.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they hear about guarding the sense faculties, they think, I must not see the eyes... the forms with my eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then just try to beat down the eyes when they do see the forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not disciplining it, that's just trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kill it off.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you do all these things that we went through, then, yeah, you will see the clarity of the mind, there, protected, through the guarding of the senses, through the not... through the... through the sustaining the context in regard to that gateway for lust and non-arisen lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you see, no, fine, I'll sustain that, I'll protect that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're doubtful, oh, okay, so this is how this obstruction could enter me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that whole talk we did on the liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Uprooting versus management.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the talk, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: The difference between uprooting and just managing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you being watchful, regardless of what you do throughout the day, means mind staying with that which is the priority.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about, oh, I have to go and do that, or I have to do this, or I have to stay here.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be going there and doing that and staying here, but the primary thing is, I stay here, guarding the gateway towards my mind, so there are no obstructions for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the sole task I have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Task that I have generated and outlined clearly for me now, on account of discipline, guarding the sense faculties, being moderate, careful with motivation in eating, and now I see it clearly, this is the gateway where the obstructions obstruct me,
[SPEAKER_00]: And when they don't obstruct me, if I don't allow them to... Yeah, now you're guarding... Yeah, you're guarding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not fighting, you're not chasing, you're just sitting at a gateway as a guard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, oh, no, you cannot enter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are in a position to do so, because you built it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the gateway is basically that, like, one entrance into the city that's completely walled around.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the wall around is your discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wall around is your sense restraint and seeing the danger in the slightest fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: The behavior has been purified for beforehand, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wall has been built.
[SPEAKER_00]: No wall.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter if you have a gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can sit at the gate and there is no wall around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not guarding.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're guarding the gate, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which nobody is interested in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody wants to go to the city.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the whole, like, sīla and celibacy is not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to be a virtuous layperson and stay a layperson, then, yeah, you can keep the five precepts and be generous.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not what we're talking about, in this talk, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, after he's disciplined in being devoted to wakefulness, the Buddha says further, kāmbeku, be possessed of mindfulness and awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, it's kind of saying the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's like composing that same wakefulness even further.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, like, bringing that, that, that context that you have developed, that, that God, God post, that you are clear about, intensifying even further now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through focusing meditation or practice, just being even clearer about it, to the point of
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to sit for half an hour and, like, you know, calm yourself down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're extending your arm, while you're extending your arm, whether you're walking, talking, going to the toilet, eating, even these, like, immediate things that you do that the mind does not necessarily pick on, and doesn't need to pick on in the beginning, even now you're not picking on them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means that even while you're doing it, that context, that guard post, is so clear, you are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not abandoning that one job that you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Protect the mind from the obstructive states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where the walking, extending, putting the rope, even these little quick things that you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, at what stage you do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason why I pointed out is because many people would start the practice with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking, focusing on my hands while I'm touching is doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no focusing there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just developing of the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the unshakable extent, be celibate, see the danger in the slightest fault, guard your sense faculties, be clear about the motivation in regard to your eating and do not allow yourself to eat out of the unwholesome motivation, watchful, and then you will know what sati-sampajañña is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the simile of a cook, who feeds the king his dishes, and then watches him, and sees, oh, he didn't take that, he took a lot of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He picks on nimittas of king's preferences, and he pays attention to significance of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time, he prepares more of that which he picked so many times, and he's skilled in reading nimittas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the other cook doesn't pick on any nimittas, and he just keeps cooking the same thing for king, and he doesn't even eat it, and then the king fires him, sends him to the dungeon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to pick the nimittas off your mind as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is your mind inclined to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pick on that before you gave in to the inclining.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, signs and features need to be discerned in the background, peripherally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something you can stare at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there are always signs and features of that which you're staring at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, seeing the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see the mind as an object of your senses, but you can discern it peripherally and know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cittanimitta.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole principle behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through this gradual practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rounding up, building up the wall, setting up the gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... And guiding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He practices full awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: The next step is, once he's accomplished in mindfulness and full awareness, the targeter disciplines him further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't be he can resort to a secluded resting place.
[SPEAKER_01]: The forest, the root of a tree, a mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do not dwell in company.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then... and then he goes... and then he resorts to a secluded resting place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Physical seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: We did talks on that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be free from hindrances, which is a prerequisite for entering the jhāna, you need to be dwelling with your mindfulness and recollectiveness thoroughly established.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to have that established, you need to be well watchful all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to have that accomplished,
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to be guarding... no, you need to be moderate in eating, don't you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you need to be guarding your sense doors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you need to be celibate and restrained by the virgins of Patimokkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you want to enter jhānas?
[SPEAKER_00]: Start being celibate here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize jhānas, as we often say, are the establishments of mind that come as a result of your purification and the lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a magical experience that will then take care of your lifestyle for you, which is what people hope.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anti-jhāna, I'm enlightened, now everything is fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jhāna is basically the last symptom, positive symptom, of you healing up everything that needs to be healed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any wound of lust, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what every jhāna formula says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dwell secluded,
[SPEAKER_00]: Removing the grief and concern in regard to the world, abandoning the hindrances, quite secluded from these unwholesome states, the pleasure of seclusion is born.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he enters and abides in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like he enters and abides in jhāna, and that's why he's secluded.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He secluded himself from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jhāna is the result of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what everybody said.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a divine abiding.
[SPEAKER_00]: When Tathāgata's mind is in jhāna, whether he walks, eats, goes to the toilet, whatever he does, it's divine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can live in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that mind, that context, that mind is so purified.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind's purified, the senses were guarded, the body has been... the senses have been tamed and basically kept within the walls.
[SPEAKER_00]: The guard post has not been abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have not been delighting in things that would be making lust increase, non-reason lust increase, and non-reason aversion manifest, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, what you have left is just the kind of... the recognition of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you haven't been giving in to that which makes hindrances overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're basically not being overwhelmed by the hindrances anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are freed from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if you abandon your celibacy, abandon your guarding of the senses, abandon your moderation eating, as the Buddhists say, you fall off from the jhāna and the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or if circumstances change to such a great extent, they just... everything becomes too unbearable, like in case of severe illnesses and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you haven't abandoned your virtue, but you can't spend your time, you know, guarding the gatepost, because you're overwhelmed by pain, half conscious, half unconscious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dying, basically, your guts are rotting, and something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you might fall away from jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if your jhāna has been developed beforehand, even then, you would not necessarily fall away from jhāna, as all the the arahants that could obtain jhānas at will, were able to endure this insane amount of discomfort and pain, because of their jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pains, they would be overwhelming a normal mind, but not painful for them, because of the jhānas that they developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But important thing, you cannot stress that enough, is jhāna is the seventh, whatever, step there, the result of all of this gradual development that, literally, in contemporary Buddhism today, is... almost everything is bypassed, and you get to jhāna first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, how convenient is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, where the actual work even for the jhāna is, you bypass all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when people say, oh, well, Bhante, didn't the Buddha enter jhāna spontaneously?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was under a root of a tree, quite secluded from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was probably...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know how old he was, but he was probably not sexually active at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was probably not chasing senses and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a kid, which means his mind was not turned towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, he's abiding, even without a jhāna, was relatively pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't have sensuality and ill-will on his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having been quite secluded from that for a while, that time when he sat under a tree waiting for his father, his mind developed that pleasure on account of seclusion, and that was the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he didn't really know the value of it at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, later on, when he thought, what if that were the way for enlightenment?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he reasoned and said, yeah, that probably is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let me do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I can't do it, because, like, I'm overwhelmed by the physical pain of this dying body that I've tortured to the point of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let me eat something, let me regain my health, and then I'll do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he did it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still the same process.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same steps.
[SPEAKER_00]: The jhāna was the result of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you get your jhāna spontaneously, it can only happen for one reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've been thoroughly withdrawn from sensuality on account of your efforts in guarding the sense doors, faculties.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what are the chances of that happening accidentally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, zero to none.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who can accidentally withdraw themselves from sensuality and see the peril of the danger in sense objects and lust and abandonment?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's virtually impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your whole being, your whole existence, is in that direction for pleasure and to avoid pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the definition of human realm, of any realm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Guided by craving in regard to feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fundamental principle behind dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you withdraw yourself from that, you don't have to worry about jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Withdrawal from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to worry about a technique or a method, which, incidentally, you will not find in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you will find a method.
[SPEAKER_00]: There it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Method is celibate eight precepts, guarding the sense doors, moderating eating, danger in the slightest fault, watchful, clear awareness, jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need more than one method.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, I told you that before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Twenty-something years ago, when I started practicing, started reading the suttas, it was Samana Pāla Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember I was reading it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he was... he has the similar passage there, when the Buddha describes that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a similar kind of training.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I remember reading it at the time, and it was all like, yeah, yeah, this is great.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I still had the views back in the in the early days, like 99, 2000, that... because, you know, everything else you read about Buddhism is about these techniques and experiences, and jhāna 1, jhāna 2, and enlightenment, and you have all these preconceived notions about what enlightenment is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with all that still being in my mind, I was reading sutta, and it was like, kind of, yeah, but come on, tell me exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I do for that jhāna and for that enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: As if everything else I read up to that point was not exact enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it wasn't exact enough, because I expected more.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted something more focused, more particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you actually start thinking about it, you say, well, wait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have I fulfilled the first step?
[SPEAKER_00]: Have I fulfilled the second step?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, let me fulfill these steps, and then, if I need something for focusing, then I'll ask for focusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you realize, if you fulfill all these other steps, you will have the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, the Buddha said, like a... like a... what was it?
[SPEAKER_00]: A hand sitting on her eggs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if she doesn't wish for her chicks to piss out safely, they will, because she did the work of sitting and keeping the eggs warm.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you fulfill all these steps, perfect your virtue, perfect the indriyājana, the slightest fault, watchfulness, moderate in eating, you will have the jhāna, you will have this passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a matter of, oh, I did everything right, but I still don't have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't have it, means you haven't done anything right, or not sufficiently right enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible to not have results, if practice has been undertaken correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you use that to review yourself as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are there results to show for?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, as we used to chant in the temples back in the day,
[SPEAKER_00]: How well am I spending my life?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will I be ashamed when questioned by my companions in holy life?
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, if I'm dying and my companions come to interrogate me and see if I'm an arahant and how much this person... as they used to do today.
[SPEAKER_00]: People don't do that, but back in the day there was a norm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's go before he dies and see what he understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, how many suttas you got that in?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you use that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so if I'm questioned on my deathbed, am I an arahant actually?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I better become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use that to make yourself strive even more, because if you strive rightly, you would have to be an arahant, or at least an anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't say at the deathbed, no, no, no, my friends in holy life, I have, guarantee you, 100% fulfill Buddha's instruction, but I'm not even a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is like to say, oh, I've been living in this desert and the sun for 50 years of my life, but these clothes are still wet, miraculously.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would have to dry.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, so, is there dispassion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there proper seclusion from hindrances, from unreasoned hindrances to arise?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I see them free from that as well?
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop clarity in regard to that, you're developing clarity in regard to jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a method.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just not the method that most people would expect, or want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the method you want, but the method you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The method everybody needs.